<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="..\transforms\pp2html.xsl"?>
<PP xmlns="http://common-criteria.rhcloud.com/ns/cc" name="Email Clients">
  <PPReference title="PP Reference" id="ID003">
    <ReferenceTable>
      <PPTitle>Application Software Extended Package for Email Clients</PPTitle>
      <PPVersion>Draft 1.6</PPVersion>
      <PPAuthor>National Information Assurance Partnership</PPAuthor>
      <PPPubDate>2015-03-02</PPPubDate>
      <PPCertificationID>unassigned</PPCertificationID>
      <CCVersion>Version 3.1</CCVersion>
      <Keywords>email; email client</Keywords>
      <entry>
        <name>Registration</name>
        <description>National Information Assurance Partnership</description>
      </entry>
    </ReferenceTable>
  </PPReference>
  <RevisionHistory role="draft">
    <entry>
      <version>v 1.0</version>
      <date>2014-04-01</date>
      <subject>Release - Email Client Protection Profile</subject>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <version>v 1.5 </version>
      <date>2014-12-11</date>
      <subject>Interim Draft - Update as Extended Package of the Protection Profile for Application
        Software</subject>
    </entry>
  </RevisionHistory>
  <chapter title="Introduction" id="int">
    <section title="Overview" id="ppoverview">The scope of this Extended Package (EP) is to describe
      the security functionality of email clients in terms of <cite linkend="bibCC"/>. This EP is
      not complete in itself, but rather extends the security requirements of the Protection Profile
      for Application Software (<cite linkend="bibAppPP"/>). </section>
    <section id="glossary" title="Terms">The following sections provide both Common Criteria and
      technology terms used in this Extended Package. <subsection title="Common Criteria Terms"
        id="ccterms">
        <glossary>
          <entry>
            <term><abbr title="Common Criteria">CC</abbr></term>
            <description>Common Criteria for Information Technology Security
              Evaluation.</description>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <term><abbr title="Common Evaluation Methodology">CEM</abbr></term>
            <description>Common Evaluation Methodology for Information Technology Security
              Evaluation.</description>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <term><abbr title="Extended Package">EP</abbr></term>
            <description>An implementation-independent set of security requirements for a category
              of products, which extends those in a Protection Profile.</description>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <term><abbr title="Protection Profile">PP</abbr></term>
            <description>An implementation-independent set of security requirements for a category
              of products.</description>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <term><abbr title="Security Target">ST</abbr></term>
            <description>A set of implementation-dependent security requirements for a specific
              product.</description>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <term><abbr title="Target of Evaluation">TOE</abbr></term>
            <description>The product under evaluation. In this case, application software and its
              supporting documentation.</description>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <term><abbr title="TOE Security Functionality">TSF</abbr></term>
            <description>The security functionality of the product under evaluation.</description>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <term><abbr title="TOE Summary Specification">TSS</abbr></term>
            <description>A description of how a <abbr linkend="TOE"/> satisfies the SFRs in a <abbr
                linkend="ST"/>. </description>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <term><abbr title="Security Functional Requirement">SFR</abbr></term>
            <description>A requirement for security enforcement by the <abbr linkend="TOE"/>.
            </description>
          </entry>
        </glossary>
      </subsection>
      <subsection id="techterms" title="Technology Terms">
        <glossary>
          <entry>
            <term>ActiveSync</term>
            <description>Microsoft protocol for synchronizing data between mobile and desktop
              environments.</description>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <term>Add-on</term>
            <description>Capabilities or functionality added to an application including plug-ins,
              extensions or other controls.</description>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <term>IMAP</term>
            <description>Internet Message Access Protocol - Protocol for an email client to retrieve
              email from an email server over TCP/IP; IMAP4 defined in RFC 3501.</description>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <term>MAPI</term>
            <description>Messaging Application Programming Interface for HTTP - Protocol used by
              Microsoft Exchange for sending/receiving email; defined in <cite linkend="bibmapispec"
              />. </description>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <term>MTA</term>
            <description>Mail Transfer Agent</description>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <term>POP</term>
            <description>Post Office Protocol - Protocol for an email client to retrieve email from
              an email server over TCP/IP; POP3 defined in RFC 1939.</description>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <term>RPC</term>
            <description>Remote Procedure Call - Protocol used by Microsoft Exchange to send/receive
              MAPI commands; defined in MS-OXCRPC.</description>
          </entry>
          <entry>
            <term>SMTP</term>
            <description>Simple Mail Transfer Protocol - Protocol for an email client to send email
              to an email server over TCP/IP; SMTP defined in RFC 5321.</description>
          </entry>
        </glossary>
      </subsection>
    </section>
    <section title="Compliant Targets of Evaluation" id="TOEdescription"> This document provides an
      extended set of Security Functional Requirements (SFRs) for an email client, which is the
      Target of Evaluation (TOE). <br/> The Protection Profile for Application Software (App PP)
      defines the baseline SFRs for application software which runs on mobile devices ("apps"), as
      well as on desktop and server platforms. This Extended Package (EP) for email clients is not
      complete in itself, but rather extends the baseline of App PP. <br/> Email clients are
      applications used to send, receive, access and manage email provided by an email server. The
      complexity of email content and email clients has grown over time. Modern email clients can
      render HTML as well as plaintext, and may include functionality to display common attachment
      formats, such as Adobe PDF and Microsoft Word documents. Some email clients allow their
      functionality to be modified by users through the addition of add-ons. This complex and rich
      feature set makes email clients a target for attackers. Protocols have also been defined for
      communicating between email clients and servers. Some clients support multiple protocols for
      doing the same task, allowing them to be configured according to email server specifications. </section>
    <section title="Use Cases" id="usecases">Email clients perform tasks associated primarily with
      the following use case. <usecases>
        <usecase title="Sending, receiving, accessing, managing and displaying email">
          <description>Email clients are used for sending, receiving, viewing, accessing, managing
            email in coordination with a mail server. Email clients can render HTML as well as
            plaintext, and can display common attachment formats. </description>
        </usecase>
      </usecases>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter title="Conformance Claims" id="conf">
    <cclaims>
      <cclaim id="Conformance Statement">
        <description> The Protection Profile for Application Software (App PP) defines the baseline
          Security Functional Requirements (SFRs) and Security Assurance Requirements (SARs) for
          application software products. This EP serves to extend the App PP baseline with
          additional SFRs and associated Assurance Activities specific to an email client. Assurance
          Activities are the actions that the evaluator performs in order to determine a TOE’s
          compliance to the SFRs.<br/> This EP conforms to Common Criteria <cite linkend="bibCC"/>
          for Information Technology Security Evaluation, Version 3.1, Revision 4. It is CC Part 2
          extended and CC Part 3 conformant. In order to be conformant to this EP, the ST must
          include all components in this EP and the associated App PP that are:
              <ul><li>unconditional (which are always required)</li>
            <li>selection-based (which are required when certain selections are chosen in the
              unconditional requirements)</li>
          </ul> and may include components that are: <ul><li>optional or</li>
            <li>objective.</li></ul></description>
      </cclaim>
    </cclaims>
  </chapter>
  <chapter title="Security Problem Description" id="spd"> The security problem is described in terms
    of the threats that the email client is expected to address, assumptions about the operational
    environment, and any organizational security policies that it is expected to enforce. <br/> This
    Extended Package does not repeat the threats, assumptions, and organizational security policies
    identified in the App PP, though they all apply given the conformance and hence dependence of
    this EP on it. Together the threats, assumptions and organizational security policies of the App
    PP and those defined in this EP describe those addressed by an email client as the Target of
    Evaluation. <br/> Notably, email clients are particularly at risk from the Network Attack threat
    identified in the App PP. Attackers can send malicious email messages directly to users, and the
    email client will render or otherwise process this untrusted content. <section title="Threats"
      id="threats">The following threat is specific to email clients, and represents an addition to
      those identified in the App PP. <threats>
        <threat id="T.FLAWED_ADDON">
          <description> Email client functionality can be extended with integration of third-party
            utilities and tools. This expanded set of capabilities is made possible via the use of
            add-ons. The tight integration between the basic email client code and the new
            capabilities that add-ons provide increases the risk that malefactors could inject
            serious flaws into the email client application, either maliciously by an attacker, or
            accidentally by a developer. These flaws enable undesirable behaviors including, but not
            limited to, allowing unauthorized access to sensitive information in the email client,
            unauthorized access to the device's file system, or even privilege escalation that
            enables unauthorized access to other applications or the operating system.
          </description>
        </threat>
      </threats>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter title="Security Objectives" id="sobj"> This Extended Package adds security objectives to
    those identified in the Protection Profile for Application Software (App PP). <section
      title="Security Objectives for the TOE" id="SecurityObjectivesTOE">
      <SOs>
        <SO id="O.ADDON_INTEGRITY">
          <description> To address issues associated with malicious or flawed plug-ins or
            extensions, conformant email clients implement mechanisms to ensure their integrity.
            This includes verification at installation time and update. </description>
          <component-refer ref="fia_x509_ext.2.4"/>
          <component-refer ref="fpt_tud_ext.2"/>
        </SO>
      </SOs>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter title="Security Requirements" id="req">This chapter describes the security requirements
    which have to be fulfilled by the <abbr linkend="TOE"/>. Those requirements comprise functional
    components from Part 2 of <cite linkend="bibCC"/>. The following notations are used: <ul>
      <li>
        <b>Selection</b> (denoted by <i>italicized text</i>): is used to select one or more options
        provided by the [CC] in stating a requirement.</li>
      <li>
        <b>Assignment</b> operation (denoted by <i>italicized text</i>): is used to assign a
        specific value to an unspecified parameter, such as the length of a password. Showing the
        value in square brackets indicates assignment.</li>
      <li>
        <b>Iteration</b> operation: are identified with a number inside parentheses (e.g.
        "(1)").</li>
    </ul>
    <section title="Security Functional Requirements" id="sfr">The Security Functional Requirements
      included in this section are derived from Part 2 of the Common Criteria for Information
      Technology Security Evaluation, Version 3.1, Revision 4, with additional extended functional
      components. <subsection title="Cryptographic Support (FCS)" id="fcs">
        <f-component id="FCS_SMIME_EXT.1"
          name="Secure/Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions (S/MIME)">
          <f-element id="FCS_SMIME_EXT.1.1">
            <title>The email client shall implement both a sending and receiving S/MIME v3.2 Agent
              as defined in RFC 5751, using CMS as defined in RFCs 5652, 5754, and 3565. </title>
            <note role="application"> The RFCs allow for an agent to be either sending or receiving,
              or to include both capabilities. The intent of this requirement is to ensure that the
              email client is capable of both sending and receiving S/MIME v3.2 messages. </note>
          </f-element>
          <f-element id="FCS_SMIME_EXT.1.2">
            <title>The email client shall transmit the Content Encryption Algorithm Identifier for
              AES-128 CBC and <selectables>
                <selectable>AES-256 CBC</selectable>
                <selectable>no others</selectable>
              </selectables>. </title>
            <note role="application"> AES was added to CMS as defined in RFC 3565.</note>
          </f-element>
          <f-element id="FCS_SMIME_EXT.1.3">
            <title>The email client shall present the digest Algorithm field with the following
              Message Digest Algorithm identifiers <selectables>
                <selectable>id-sha256</selectable>
                <selectable>id-sha384</selectable>
                <selectable>id-sha512</selectable>
              </selectables> and no others. </title>
          </f-element>
          <f-element id="FCS_SMIME_EXT.1.4">
            <title>The email client shall present the Algorithm Identifier field with the following
              sha256withRSAEncryption and <selectables linebreak="yes">
                <selectable>sha384WithRSAEncryption</selectable>
                <selectable>sha512WithRSAEncryption</selectable>
                <selectable>ecdsa-with-SHA256</selectable>
                <selectable>ecdsa-with-sha384</selectable>
                <selectable>ecdsa-with-sha512</selectable>
              </selectables> and no other algorithms. </title>
            <note role="application"> RFC 5751 mandates that receiving and sending agents support
              RSA with SHA256. The algorithms to be tested in the evaluated configuration are
              limited by this requirement. Any other algorithms implemented that do not comply with
              these requirements should not be included in an evaluated email client. The ECDSA
              algorithms listed above are preferred for implementation and will be mandated in
              future versions of this EP. </note>
          </f-element>
          <f-element id="FCS_SMIME_EXT.1.5">
            <title>The email client shall use separate private keys (and associated certificates)
              for signature and for encryption. </title></f-element>
          <f-element id="FCS_SMIME_EXT.1.6">
            <title>The email client shall only accept a signature from a certificate with the
              digitalSignature bit set. </title>
            <note role="application"> It is acceptable to assume that the digitalSignature bit is
              set in cases where there is no keyUsage extension. </note>
          </f-element>
          <f-element id="FCS_SMIME_EXT.1.7">
            <title>The email client shall implement mechanisms for retrieval of Certificate
              Revocation Lists (CRLs) and certificates <selectables linebreak="yes">
                <selectable>each time needed</selectable>
                <selectable>for incoming/outgoing messages</selectable>
                <selectable>periodically</selectable>
              </selectables>.</title>
            <note role="application"> The email client can define how this mechanism behaves, but it
              is required that a mechanism exist such that revocation status is supported via CRLs
              and so that certificates can be retrieved for sending/receiving messages. In this
              requirement ―periodically‖ can be interpreted as a one-time function with local
              storage, as a regularly scheduled retrieval, or as a mechanism that requires manual
              intervention. If the retrieval mechanism is periodic in nature, then the ST author
              will need to include an iteration of FCS for storage of CRLs; storage of certificates
              is covered in FCS_CKM. The import of certificates and certificate chains is not
              included in this requirement, but is covered in FIA_X509 and FMT_MOF. </note>
            <aactivity>
              <br/> The evaluator shall check the description of the implementation of S/MIME in the
              TSS to ensure that the proper version is specified. In addition, the evaluator shall
              verify that the algorithms supported are specified, and that the algorithms specified
              are those listed for this component. The evaluator shall also review the Operational
              Guidance to ensure that it contains instructions on configuring the email client such
              that it complies to the description in the TSS.<br/> The evaluator shall verify that
              the TSS describes the ContentEncryptionAlgorithmIdentifier and whether the required
              behavior is performed by default or may be configured. If the TSS indicates that the
              algorithms must be configured to meet the requirement, the evaluator shall verify that
              the AGD guidance includes the configuration of this ID.<br/> The evaluator shall
              verify that the TSS describes the digestAlgorithm and whether the required behavior is
              performed by default or may be configured. If the TSS indicates that the algorithms
              must be configured to meet the requirement, the evaluator shall verify that the AGD
              guidance includes the configuration.<br/> The evaluator shall verify that the TSS
              describes the AlgorithmIdentifier and whether the required behavior is performed by
              default or may be configured. If the TSS indicates that the algorithms must be
              configured to meet the requirement, the evaluator shall verify that the AGD guidance
              includes the configuration of this ID.<br/> The evaluator shall verify that the TSS
              describes the retrieval mechanisms for both CRLs and certificates as well as the
              frequency at which these mechanisms are implemented. If the TSS indicates that the
              mechanisms are configurable, the evaluator shall verify that the AGD guidance includes
              the configuration of these mechanisms.<br/> The evaluator shall perform the following
              tests:<br/> These tests can be performed in conjunction with the tests defined in
              FIA_X509 for certificate/certificate chain verification. <testlist>
                <test>The evaluator shall both send and receive a message with no protection (no
                  signature or encryption) and verify that the message is transmitted properly and
                  can be viewed at the receiving agent. This transmission can be performed as part
                  of a number of mechanisms; it is sufficient to observe that the message arrives at
                  the intended recipient with the same content as when sent.</test>
                <test>The evaluator shall both send and receive a signed message using each of the
                  algorithms specified in the ST corresponding to the requirement. In addition, the
                  evaluator shall use a man-in-the-middle tool to modify at least one byte of the
                  message such that the signature is no longer valid. This can be done by modifying
                  the content of the message over which the signature is calculated or by modifying
                  the signature itself. The evaluator shall verify that the received message fails
                  the signature validation check. </test>
                <test>The evaluator shall both send and receive an encrypted message using each of
                  the algorithms specified in the ST. S/MIME is intended for end-to-end security. As
                  a result, it is not possible to have a third party inspecting email and also have
                  secure end-to-end communications. Therefore, it is not necessary to examine the
                  encrypted traffic in an attempt to determine the ciphersuite and the proper
                  implementation. In addition, the evaluator shall use a man-in-the-middle tool to
                  modify at least one byte of the message such that the encryption is no longer
                  valid. The evaluator shall verify that the received message fails to decrypt. </test>
                <test>The evaluator shall both send and receive a message that is both signed and
                  encrypted. It is not necessary to examine the encrypted traffic to meet the intent
                  of the requirement. In addition, the evaluator shall use a man-in-the-middle tool
                  to modify at least one byte of the message such that the encryption and signature
                  are no longer valid. The evaluator shall verify that the received message fails to
                  decrypt, fails the signature validation check, and/or both. </test>
                <test>The evaluator shall send a signed message to the email client using a
                  signature algorithm not supported according to the digestAlgorithm ID (e.g.,
                  SHA1). The evaluator shall verify that the email client does not accept the
                  message. </test>
                <test>The evaluator shall send an encrypted message to the email client using an
                  encryption algorithm not supported according to the AlgorithmIdentifier field. The
                  evaluator shall verify that the email client does not accept the message. </test>
                <test>The evaluator shall send the email client a message signed by a certificate
                  without the digitalSignature bit set. The evaluator shall verify that the email
                  client notifies the user that the signature is invalid. </test>
                <test>The evaluator shall send the email client a message signed by a certificate
                  without the Email Protection purpose in the extendedKeyUsage. The evaluator shall
                  verify that the email client notifies the user that the signature is
                  invalid.</test>
              </testlist>
            </aactivity>
          </f-element>
        </f-component>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="User Data Protection (FDP)" id="fdp">
        <f-component id="FDP_NOT_EXT.2" name="Notification of S/MIME Status">
          <f-element id="FDP_NOT_EXT.2.1">
            <title>The email client shall display a notification of the S/MIME status of received
              emails upon viewing.</title>
            <note role="application"> S/MIME status is whether the email has been signed or
              encrypted and whether the signature verifies and the associated certificate validates.
              This notification satisfies FIA_X509_EXT.2.6. This notification must at least display
              when the email content is viewed. Many implementations also display the S/MIME status
              of each email when all emails are viewed as a list. </note>
            <aactivity> The evaluator shall ensure that the TSS describes notifications of S/MIME
              status, including whether S/MIME status is also indicated upon viewing a list of
              emails.<br/> The evaluator shall verify that the AGD guidance proves a description
              (with appropriate visual figures) of the S/MIME status notification(s), including how
              each of encryption, verified and validated signature, and unverified and unvalidated
              signature are indicated.<br/> The evaluator shall perform the following tests and may
              perform them in conjunction with the tests for FCS_SMIME_EXT.1:<br/>
              <testlist>
                <test>The evaluator shall send the client an unencrypted and unsigned email and
                  verify that no notifications are present upon viewing.</test>
                <test>The evaluator shall send the client an encrypted email and verify that the
                  encrypted notification is present upon viewing.</test>
                <test>The evaluator shall send the client a valid signed email and verify that the
                  signed notification is present upon viewing.</test>
                <test>The evaluator shall send the client an invalid signed email (for example,
                  using a certificate that does not contain the correct email address or a
                  certificate that does not chain to the root store) and verify that the invalid
                  signature notification is present upon viewing.</test>
              </testlist>
            </aactivity>
          </f-element>
        </f-component>
        <f-component id="FDP_NOT_EXT.3" name="Notification of URI">
          <f-element id="FDP_NOT.EXT.3.1">
            <title>The email client shall display the full Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) of any
              embedded links.</title>
            <note role="application"> Embedded links are HTML URI objects which may have a tag (such
              as a word, phrase, icon, or picture) that obfuscates the URI of the link. The intent
              of this requirement is de-obfuscate the link. The URI may be displayed as a
              ―mouse-over‖ event or may be rendered next to the tag. </note>
            <aactivity> The evaluator shall verify that the TSS includes a description of how
              embedded links are rendered and the method by which the URI of the link is
              displayed.<br/> The evaluator shall ensure that the AGD guidance includes instruction
              (with any appropriate visual figures) for viewing the URI of an embedded link.<br/>
              The evaluator shall perform the following test:<br/>
              <testlist>
                <test>The evaluator shall send the client an HTML message with an embedded link
                  whose tag is not the URI itself (for example, ―click here‖). The evaluator shall
                  view the message and following the instructions in the AGD guidance verify that
                  the full URI of the embedded link is displayed. </test></testlist>
            </aactivity>
          </f-element>
        </f-component>
        <f-component id="FDP_PST_EXT.1" name="Storage of Persistent Information">
          <f-element id="FDP_PST_EXT.1.1" status="objective">
            <title>The email client shall be capable of operating without storing persistent
              information to the file system.</title>
            <note role="application">Exceptions from this requirement are credentials and
              configuration information.</note>
            <aactivity>The evaluator shall operate the email client for a period of time, ensuring
              that a wide variety of email client functionality has been exercised. The evaluator
              shall then examine the email client to ensure that no files have been written to the
              file system other than credentials or configuration information.</aactivity>
          </f-element>
        </f-component>
        <f-component id="FDP_REN_EXT.1" name="Rendering of Message Content">
          <f-element id="FDP_REN_EXT.1.1">
            <title>The email client shall have a plaintext only mode.</title>
            <note role="application"> Plaintext only mode prevents the automatic downloading of
              images and rendering and execution of embedded objects such as HTML or JavaScript
              objects. FMT_SMF.1.1 function 3 addresses configuration of this mode. </note>
            <aactivity> The evaluator shall ensure that the TSS describes plaintext only mode for
              sending and receiving messages. The evaluator shall verify that the TSS describes
              whether the email client is capable of rendering and executing HTML or JavaScript. If
              the email client can render or execute HTML or JavaScript, this description must
              indicate how the email client handles received messages that contain HTML or
              JavaScript while in plaintext only mode, and the evaluator shall ensure that that
              description indicates that embedded objects of these types are not rendered or
              executed and that images are not automatically downloaded.<br/> The evaluator shall
              examine the AGD guidance and verify that it contains instructions for enabling
              plaintext only mode.<br/> The evaluator shall perform the following tests:<br/>
              <testlist>
                <test>(conditional) If the email client is capable of rendering HTML, the evaluator
                  shall send a message to the client containing HTML embedded objects and shall
                  verify that the HTML renders. The evaluator shall then enable plaintext only mode
                  and verify that the HTML does not render.</test>
                <test>(conditional) If the email client is capable of rendering and executing
                  JavaScript, the evaluator shall send a message to the client containing JavaScript
                  embedded objects and shall verify that the JavaScript renders and executes. The
                  evaluator shall then enable plaintext only mode and verify that the JavaScript
                  does not render or execute.</test>
              </testlist>
            </aactivity>
          </f-element>
        </f-component>
        <f-component id="FDP_SMIME_EXT.1" name="S/MIME">
          <f-element id="FDP_SMIME_EXT.1.1">
            <title>The email client shall use Secure/Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions (S/MIME)
              to sign, verify, encrypt, and decrypt mail.</title>
            <note role="application">S/MIME is used to sign messages at the request of the user
              (FMT_SMF.1.1 Function 7) upon sending email via the Mail Transfer Agent. S/MIME is
              used by a recipient to verify the digital signature on a signed message upon receipt
              or viewing of the message. Encryption of messages occurs at the request of the user
              (FMT_SMF.1.1 Function 8) upon sending email via the Mail Transfer Agent, and
              decryption of emails occurs upon receipt or viewing of the message. Note that this
              requirement does not mandate that S/MIME be used for all incoming/outgoing messages,
              or that the email client automatically encrypt and/or sign/verify all sent or received
              messages. This requirement only specifies that the mechanism for digital signature and
              encryption must be S/MIME.</note>
            <aactivity>The evaluator shall verify that the TSS contains a description of the S/MIME
              implementation and its use to protect mail from undetected modification using digital
              signatures and unauthorized disclosure using encryption. The evaluator shall verify
              that the TSS describes whether signature verification and decryption occur at receipt
              or viewing of the message contents, and whether messages are stored with their S/MIME
              envelopes.<br/> The evaluator shall ensure that the AGD guidance includes instructions
              for configuring a certificate for S/MIME use and instructions for signing and
              encrypting email.<br/> Tests for this element are performed in conjunction with tests
              for FCS_SMIME_EXT.1, FDP_NOT_EXT.1, and FMT_SMF.1.</aactivity><br/>
          </f-element>
        </f-component>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Identification and Authentication (FIA)" id="fia">
        <f-component id="FIA_SASL_EXT.1" name="Simple Authentication and Security Layer (SASL)">
          <f-element id="FIA_SASL_EXT.1.1">
            <title>The email client shall implement support for Simple Authentication and Security
              Layer (SASL) that complies with RFC 4422. </title>
            <br/>
            <aactivity> The evaluator shall examine the TSS to determine that it describes the
              details of the email client connecting to Mail User Agent and a Mail Transfer Agent in
              terms of the SASL connection, along with email client -specific options or procedures
              that might not be reflected in the specification.<br/> The evaluator shall confirm
              that the operational guidance contains instructions for establishing the connection to
              the Mail User Agent and the Mail Transfer Agent. The evaluator shall also perform the
              following test:<br/>
              <br/>
              <testlist>
                <test>The evaluators shall ensure that the email client is able to initiate
                  communications with a Mail User Agent using POP, IMAP, and any assigned protocols
                  specified in the requirement, setting up the connections as described in the
                  operational guidance and ensuring that communication is successful.</test>
                <test>The evaluators shall verify that a successful SASL handshake takes place. To
                  perform this test, the evaluator shall use a sniffer and a packet analyzer. The
                  packet analyzer must indicate that the protocol in use is SASL.</test>
              </testlist>
            </aactivity>
          </f-element>
          <f-element id="FIA_SASL_EXT.1.2">
            <title>The email client must support the POP3 CAPA and AUTH extensions for the SASL
              mechanism. </title>
          </f-element>
          <f-element id="FIA_SASL_EXT.1.3">
            <title>The email client must support the IMAP CAPABILITY and AUTHENTICATE extensions for
              the SASL mechanism. </title>
          </f-element>
          <f-element id="FIA_SASL_EXT.1.4">
            <title>The email client must support the SMTP AUTH extension for the SASL mechanism. </title>
            <note role="application"> In order for an email clients to support PKI X.509
              Certificates for POP3, IMAP and SMTP as required in this document, the client must
              support the Simple Authentication and Security Layer (SASL) authentication method as
              described in RFC 4422, the AUTH and CAPA extensions for POP3, as described in RFC
              5043, the AUTHENTICATION and CAPABILITY extensions for IMAP, as described in RFC 4959
              and the AUTH extension for SMTP, as described in RFC 4954. </note>
            <aactivity> The evaluator shall examine the TSS to determine that it describes the
              details of the email client connecting to a Mail User Agent and a Mail Transfer Agent
              in terms of the SASL connection, along with email client -specific options or
              procedures that might not be reflected in the specification.<br/> The evaluator shall
              confirm that the operational guidance contains instructions for establishing the
              connection to the Mail User Agent and the Mail Transfer Agent. The evaluator shall
              also perform the following tests:<br/>
              <testlist>
                <test>The evaluators shall ensure that the email client is able to initiate
                  communications with a Mail User Agent using POP, IMAP and SMTP and requiring SASL,
                  setting up the connections as described in the operational guidance and ensuring
                  that communication is successful.</test>
                <test>The evaluator shall ensure, for each communication channel with an authorized
                  IT entity in tests 1, that a valid SASL handshake is performed. To perform this
                  test, the evaluator shall use a sniffer and a packet analyzer. The packet analyzer
                  must indicate that the protocol in use is SASL.</test>
              </testlist>
            </aactivity>
          </f-element>
        </f-component>
        <!-- <f-component id="FIA_SMIME_EXT.1" name="S/MIME">
          <f-element id="FIA_SMIME_EXT.1.1">
            <title>The email client shall only send/receive messages using the cryptographic
              algorithms defined in FCS_SMIME_EXT.1. The TSF shall require equivalent or more robust
              algorithms to be used for encryption. </title>
            <note role="application"> While S/MIME v.3.2 requires default algorithms, these default
              algorithms are substantially weaker than required by this EP. This requirement
              indicates that the evaluated configuration of the client must disable these weaker
              algorithms. </note>
            <aactivity> The TSS description and operational guidance associated with this
              requirement are performed in conjunction with FCS_SMIME_EXT.1.<br/> The evaluator
              shall perform the following test:<br/>
              <testlist><test>The evaluator shall attempt to send the client a message signed and
                  encrypted with disallowed algorithms and shall verify that the client rejects the
                  message.</test></testlist>
            </aactivity>
          </f-element>
        </f-component> -->
        <f-component id="FIA_X509_EXT.2" name="X509 Authentication and Encryption">
          <f-element id="FIA_X509_EXT.2.1(2)">
            <title>The email client shall use X.509v3 certificates as defined by RFC 5280 to support
              encryption and authentication for S/MIME. </title>
          </f-element>
          <f-element id="FIA_X509_EXT.2.3">
            <title> The email client shall prevent the establishment of a trusted communication
              channel when the peer certificate is deemed invalid. </title>
            <note role="application"> Trusted communication channels include any of TLS performed by
              the TSF. Validity is determined by the certificate path, the expiration date, and the
              revocation status in accordance with RFC 5280. </note>
          </f-element>
          <f-element id="FIA_X509_EXT.2.4">
            <title> The email client shall prevent the installation of code if the code signing
              certificate is deemed invalid. </title>
            <note role="application"> Certificates may optionally be used for trusted updates of
              system software (FPT_TUD_EXT.1.3). </note>
          </f-element>
          <f-element id="FIA_X509_EXT.2.5">
            <title> The email client shall prevent the encryption of email if the email protection
              certificate is deemed invalid. </title>
          </f-element>
          <f-element id="FIA_X509_EXT.2.6">
            <title> The email client shall notify the user if an email is signed with an invalid
              certificate. </title>
            <aactivity> The evaluator shall check the TSS to ensure that it describes how the email
              client chooses which certificates to use, and any necessary instructions in the
              administrative guidance for configuring the operating environment so that the email
              client can use the certificates.<br/> The evaluator shall examine the TSS to confirm
              that it describes the behavior of the email client when a connection cannot be
              established during the validity check of a certificate used in establishing a trusted
              channel and protecting email. If the requirement that the administrator is able to
              specify the default action, then the evaluator shall ensure that the operational
              guidance contains instructions on how this configuration action is performed.<br/> The
              evaluator shall perform Test 1 for each function listed in FIA_X509_EXT.2.1 that
              requires the use of certificates:<br/>
              <testlist>
                <test>The evaluator shall demonstrate that using a certificate without a valid
                  certification path results in the function failing or in the receipt of a user
                  notification (as required by elements 3, 4, 5, and 6). The evaluator shall then
                  load into the platform’s root store any certificates needed to validate the
                  certificate to be used in the function, and demonstrate that the function succeeds
                  or results in no user notification.</test>
                <test>The evaluator shall demonstrate that using a valid certificate that requires
                  certificate validation checking to be performed in at least some part by
                  communicating with a non-TOE IT entity. The evaluator shall then manipulate the
                  environment so that the email client is unable to verify the validity of the
                  certificate, and observe that the action selected in FIA_X509_EXT.2.2 is
                  performed. If the selected action is administrator-configurable, then the
                  evaluator shall follow the operational guidance to determine that all supported
                  administrator-configurable options behave in their documented manner.</test>
              </testlist>
            </aactivity>
          </f-element>
        </f-component>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Security Management (FMT)" id="fmt">
        <f-component id="FMT_MOF_EXT.1" name="Management of Functions Behavior">
          <f-element id="FMT_MOF_EXT.1.1">
            <title>The email client shall restrict the ability to manage/perform functions as
              follows: <ul>
                <li>X = Mandatory</li>
                <li>O = Optional</li></ul>
              <table><tr class="header">
                  <td>Management Function</td><td>Administrator</td><td>User</td></tr>
                <!-- Revised -->
                <tr><td>Enable/disable downloading embedded objects globally and by <selectables>
                      <selectable>domain</selectable>
                      <selectable>sender</selectable>
                      <selectable>no other method</selectable>
                    </selectables>
                  </td><td>O</td><td>O</td></tr>
                <tr><td>Enable/disable plaintext only mode globally and by<selectables>
                      <selectable>domain</selectable>
                      <selectable>sender</selectable>
                      <selectable>no other method</selectable>
                    </selectables>
                  </td><td>O</td><td>O</td></tr>
                <tr><td>Enable/disable rendering and execution of attachments globally and by<selectables>
                      <selectable>domain</selectable>
                      <selectable>sender</selectable>
                      <selectable>no other method</selectable></selectables>
                  </td><td>O</td><td>O</td></tr>
                <tr><td> Configure
                        <selectables><selectable>visual</selectable><selectable>auditory</selectable></selectables>
                    email notifications to display <selectables>
                      <selectable>number of emails received</selectable>
                      <selectable>subject</selectable>
                      <selectable>sender</selectable>
                      <selectable>partial content</selectable></selectables>
                  </td><td>O</td><td>O</td></tr>
                <!-- Added to address the deleted FPD_NOT-EXT.1.1 -->
                <tr><td>Enable/disable email notifications</td>
                  <td>O</td><td>O</td></tr>
                <tr><td>Configure certificates for S/MIME use</td>
                  <td>O</td><td>O</td></tr>
                <tr><td>Configure certificates for TLS use</td>
                  <td>O</td><td>O</td></tr>
                <tr><td>Enable/disable display of email contents in email notifications</td>
                  <td>O</td><td>O</td></tr>
                <tr><td>Configure a certificate repository for encryption</td>
                  <td>O</td><td>O</td></tr>
                <tr><td>Configure whether to establish a trusted channel or disallow establishment
                    if the TSF cannot establish a connection to determine the validity of a
                    certificate</td>
                  <td>O</td><td>O</td></tr>
                <!-- FIA_SMIME_EXT.1 -->
                <tr><td>Configure message sending/receiving to only use cryptographic algorithms
                    defined in FCS_SMIME_EXT.1. </td><td>O</td><td>O</td></tr>
              </table>
              <!-- <selectables linebreak="yes">
                <selectable>Enable/disable downloading embedded objects globally and <selectables>
                    <selectable>by domain</selectable>
                    <selectable>by sender</selectable>
                    <selectable>no other method</selectable>
                  </selectables>
                </selectable>
                <selectable>Enable/disable plaintext only mode globally and <selectables>
                    <selectable>by domain</selectable>
                    <selectable>by sender</selectable>
                    <selectable>no other method</selectable>
                  </selectables>
                </selectable>
                <selectable>Enable/disable rendering and execution of attachments globally and <selectables>
                    <selectable>by domain</selectable>
                    <selectable>by sender</selectable>
                    <selectable>no other method</selectable>
                  </selectables>
                </selectable>
                <selectable>Configure <selectables>
                    <selectable>visual</selectable>
                    <selectable>auditory</selectable></selectables>email notifications to
                  enable/disable display of additional information about the email <selectables>
                    <selectable>number of emails received</selectable>
                    <selectable>subject</selectable>
                    <selectable>sender</selectable>
                    <selectable>partial content</selectable></selectables></selectable> -->
              <!-- Added to address the deleted FPD_NOT-EXT.1.1 -->
              <!-- <selectable>Enable/disable email notifications</selectable>
              <selectable>Configure certificates for S/MIME use</selectable>
              <selectable>Configure certificates for TLS use</selectable>
              <selectable>Enable/disable display of email contents in email
                notifications</selectable>
              <selectable>Configure a certificate repository for encryption</selectable>
              <selectable>Configure whether to establish a trusted channel or disallow establishment
                if the TSF cannot establish a connection to determine the validity of a
                certificate</selectable>
              <selectable>No other management functions</selectable> -->
            </title>
            <note role="application"> The Administrator is responsible for management activities,
              including setting the policy that is applied by the enterprise on the email client.
              This administrator is likely to be acting remotely and could be the MTA administrator
              acting through a centralized management console or dashboard.<br/> The intent of this
              requirement is to allow the administrator to configure the email client with a policy
              that may not be over-ridden by the user. If the administrator has not set a policy for
              a particular function, the user may still perform that function. Enforcement of the
              policy is done by the email cient itself, or the email client and the email client
              platform in coordination with each other.<br/> For Function #9 per FIA_X509_EXT.2.2,
              the administrator has the option of accepting or rejecting all certificates that
              cannot be validated, accepting a given certificate that cannot be validated, or not
              accepting a given certificate that cannot be validated. Depending on the choice that
              the administrator has made in FIA_X509_EXT.2.2, the trusted connection will either be
              allowed for all certificates that cannot be validated, disallowed for all certificates
              cannot be validated, allowed for a given certificate that cannot be validated, or
              disallowed for a given certificate that cannot be validated. </note>
            <aactivity> The evaluator shall perform the following tests:<br/>
              <testlist>
                <test>The evaluator shall use the test environment to deploy policies to the email
                  client.</test>
                <test>The evaluator shall create policies which collectively include all management
                  functions which are controlled by the (enterprise) administrator and cannot be
                  overridden by the user as defined in FMT_MOF.1.1(2). The evaluator shall apply
                  these policies to the client, attempt to override each setting as the user, and
                  ensure that the TSF does not permit it.</test>
              </testlist></aactivity>
          </f-element>
        </f-component>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Protection of the TSF (FPT)" id="fpt">
        <f-component id="FPT_TUD_EXT.1" name="Support for Trusted Add-ons">
          <f-element id="FPT_TUD_EXT.1.1">
            <title>The email client shall include the capability to load <selectables>
                <selectable>no add-ons</selectable>
                <selectable>trusted email client add-ons</selectable>
              </selectables>.</title>
          </f-element>
        </f-component>
        <f-component id="FPT_TUD_EXT.2" name="Trusted Installation and Updates for Add-ons">
          <f-element id="FPT_TUD_EXT.2.1" status="sel-based">
            <selection-depends req="FPT_TUD_EXT.1.1"/>
            <title>The email client shall provide the ability to query the current version of the
              add-on.</title>
          </f-element>
          <f-element id="FPT_TUD_EXT.2.2" status="sel-based">
            <selection-depends req="FPT_TUD_EXT.1.1"/>
            <title>The email client shall provide the ability to initiate the downloading of add-ons
              and add-on updates.</title>
          </f-element>
          <f-element id="FPT_TUD_EXT.2.3" status="sel-based">
            <selection-depends req="FPT_TUD_EXT.1.1"/>
            <title>The email client shall provide a means to verify add-ons using a digital
              signature mechanism and <selectables>
                <selectable>published hash</selectable>
                <selectable>no other functions</selectable>
              </selectables> prior to installing the add-on.</title>
          </f-element>
          <f-element id="FPT_TUD_EXT.2.4" status="sel-based">
            <selection-depends req="FPT_TUD_EXT.1.1"/>
            <title>The email client shall prevent the automatic installation of add-ons.</title>
          </f-element>
          <aactivity>
            <h4>TSS</h4> The evaluator shall examine the <abbr linkend="TSS"/> to verify that it
            states that the <abbr linkend="TSF"/> will reject add-ons from unapproved sources.
              <h4>Guidance</h4> The evaluator shall examine the operational guidance to verify that
            it includes instructions on how to configure the email client with trusted add-on
            sources. <h4>Tests</h4> The evaluator shall perform the following tests:<br/>
            <testlist>
              <test>The evaluator shall configure the email client with trusted add-on sources. The
                evaluator shall create or obtain a add-on signed by a trusted source and attempt to
                install it. The evaluator shall verify that the signature on the add-on is
                valid.</test>
              <test>The evaluator shall create or obtain an add-on signed by an untrusted source and
                attempt to install it. The evaluator shall verify that the signed add-on is
                rejected.</test>
              <test>The evaluator shall create or obtain an add-on signed with an invalid
                certificate and attempt to install it. The evaluator shall verify that the signed
                add-on is valid.</test>
              <test>The evaluator shall create or obtain an add-on signed by a trusted source,
                modify the add-on without re-signing it, and attempt to install it. The evaluator
                shall verify that the signed add-on is rejected.</test>
            </testlist>
          </aactivity>
        </f-component>
      </subsection>
      <subsection title="Trusted Path/Channels (FTP)" id="ftp">
        <f-component id="FTP_ITC.1" name="Inter-TSF Trusted Channel">
          <f-element id="FTP_ITC.1.2">
            <title>The email client shall permit the <abbr linkend="TSF"/> to initiate or receive
              communication via the trusted channel. </title>
          </f-element>
          <f-element id="FTP_ITC.1.3">
            <title>The email client shall initiate communication via the trusted channel for
                <selectables linebreak="yes">
                <selectable>IMAP</selectable>
                <selectable>SMTP</selectable>
                <selectable>POP</selectable>
                <selectable>MAPI Extensions for HTTP</selectable>
                <selectable>MAPI/RPC</selectable>
                <selectable>ActiveSync</selectable>
              </selectables>. </title>
            <aactivity> The evaluator shall examine the TSS to determine that it describes the
              details of the email client connecting to Mail User Agent and a Mail Transfer Agent in
              terms of the TLS connection, along with email client-specific options or procedures
              that might not be reflected in the specification.<br/> The evaluator shall confirm
              that the operational guidance contains instructions for establishing the connection to
              the Mail User Agent and the Mail Transfer Agent. The evaluator shall also perform the
              following tests:<br/>
              <testlist>
                <test>The evaluators shall ensure that the email client is able to initiate
                  communications with a Mail User Agent using POP, IMAP and any assigned protocols
                  specified in the requirement over TLS, setting up the connections as described in
                  the operational guidance and ensuring that communication is successful.</test>
                <test>The evaluators shall ensure that the email client is able to initiate
                  communications with a Mail Transfer Agent using SMTP and any assigned protocols
                  specified in the requirement over TLS, setting up the connections as described in
                  the operational guidance and ensuring that communication is successful.</test>
                <test>The evaluator shall ensure, for each communication channel with an authorized
                  IT entity in tests 1 and 2, the channel data is not sent in plaintext. To perform
                  this test, the evaluator shall use a sniffer and a packet analyzer. The packet
                  analyzer must indicate that the protocol in use is TLS.</test>
              </testlist>
            </aactivity>
          </f-element>
        </f-component>
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <appendix title="Optional Requirements" id="optional"> As indicated in <secref linkend="ccl"/>,
    the baseline requirements (those that must be performed by the <abbr linkend="TOE"/>) are
    contained in the body of this EP. Additionally, there are three other types of requirements
    specified in <appref linkend="optional"/>, <appref linkend="sel-based"/>, and <appref
      linkend="objective"/>. The first type (in this Appendix) are requirements that can be included
    in the <abbr linkend="ST"/>, but are not required in order for an email client to claim
    conformance to this EP. The second type (in <appref linkend="sel-based"/>) are requirements
    based on selections in the body of the EP: if certain selections are made, then additional
    requirements in that appendix must be included. The third type (in <appref linkend="objective"/>
    are components that are not required in order to conform to this EP, but will be included in the
    baseline requirements in future versions of this EP, so adoption by vendors is encouraged. Note
    that the ST author is responsible for ensuring that requirements that may be associated with
    those in <appref linkend="optional"/>, <appref linkend="sel-based"/>, and <appref
      linkend="objective"/> but are not listed (e.g., FMT-type requirements) are also included in
    the ST. </appendix>
  <appendix title="Selection-Based Requirements" id="sel-based">As indicated in the introduction to
    this EP, the baseline requirements (those that must be performed by the email client or its
    underlying platform) are contained in the App PP and in the body of this EP. There are
    additional requirements based on selections from the App PP and/or in the body of the EP: if
    certain selections are made, then additional requirements below will need to be included. </appendix>
  <appendix title="Objective Requirements" id="objective"> This Annex includes requirements that
    specify security functionality which also addresses threats. The requirements are not currently
    mandated in the body of this EP as they describe security functionality not yet widely-available
    in commercial technology. However, these requirements may be included in the ST such that the
    email client is still conformant to this EP, and it is expected that they be included as soon as
    possible. </appendix>
  <appendix id="biblio" title="References">
    <bibliography>
      <entry id="bibCC">
        <tag>CC</tag>
        <description>Common Criteria for Information Technology Security Evaluation - <ul>
            <li><a href="http://www.commoncriteriaportal.org/files/ccfiles/CCPART1V3.1R4.pdf">Part
                1: Introduction and General Model</a>, CCMB-2012-09-001, Version 3.1 Revision 4,
              September 2012.</li>
            <li><a href="http://www.commoncriteriaportal.org/files/ccfiles/CCPART2V3.1R4.pdf">Part
                2: Security Functional Components</a>, CCMB-2012-09-002, Version 3.1 Revision 4,
              September 2012.</li>
            <li><a href="http://www.commoncriteriaportal.org/files/ccfiles/CCPART3V3.1R4.pdf">Part
                3: Security Assurance Components</a>, CCMB-2012-09-003, Version 3.1 Revision 4,
              September 2012.</li>
          </ul></description>
      </entry>
      <entry id="bibAppPP">
        <tag>AppPP</tag>
        <description>
          <a href="https://www.niap-ccevs.org/pp/">Protection Profile for Application Software</a>
        </description>
      </entry>
      <entry id="bibmapispec">
        <tag>MS-OXCMAPIHTTP</tag>
        <description>
          <a href="https://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/dn530952(v=exchg.80).aspx"> Messaging
            Application Programming Interface (MAPI) Extensions for HTTP</a>
        </description>
      </entry>
    </bibliography>
  </appendix>
  <appendix title="Acronyms" id="acronyms">
    <acronyms>
      <entry>
        <term>AES</term>
        <description>Advanced Encryption Standard</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>CBC</term>
        <description>Cipher Block Chaining</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>CRL</term>
        <description>Certificate Revocation List</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>CSP</term>
        <description>Cryptographic Service Provider</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>DHE</term>
        <description>Diffie-Hellman Key Exchange</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>DN</term>
        <description>Distinguished Name</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>DSA</term>
        <description>Digital Signature Algorithm</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>ECC</term>
        <description>Elliptic Curve Cryptography</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>ECDSA</term>
        <description>Elliptic Curve Digital Signature Algorithm</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>EP</term>
        <description>Extended Package</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>FFC</term>
        <description>Finite-Field Cryptography</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>FIPS</term>
        <description>Federal Information Processing Standards</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>GCM</term>
        <description>Galois/Counter Mode</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>HMAC</term>
        <description>Keyed Hash Message Authentication Code</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>HTML</term>
        <description>HyperText Markup Language</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>HTTP</term>
        <description>HyperText Transfer Protocol</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>HTTPS</term>
        <description>HyperText Transfer Protocol Secure</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>IETF</term>
        <description>Internet Engineering Task Force</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>IV</term>
        <description>Initialization Vector</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>KAT</term>
        <description>Known Answer Test</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>KDF</term>
        <description>Key Derivation Function</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>NIST</term>
        <description>National Institute of Standards and Technology</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>OCSP</term>
        <description>Online Certificate Status Protocol</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>OID</term>
        <description>Object Identifier</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>PDF</term>
        <description>Portable Document Format</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>RFC</term>
        <description>Request for Comment (IETF)</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>RSA</term>
        <description>Rivest Shamir Adelman</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>SHA</term>
        <description>Secure Hash Algorithm</description>
      </entry>
      <entry>
        <term>TLS</term>
        <description>Transport Layer Security</description>
      </entry>
    </acronyms>
  </appendix>
</PP>
